Preliminary Guide to the Fritz London Papers, 1922 - 1994 UA.29.02.0071
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fritz London papers
1922-2008, bulk 1926-1954
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
London, Fritz, 1900-1954
UA.29.02.0071
7.6 Linear Feet 3,500 items
Fritz London, physicist and theoretical chemist, formulated the London equations of superconductivity with his brother, Heinz London. After fleeing Nazi Germany in 1933, London held appointments at Oxford and Paris, then at Duke University from 1939 to 1954. He specialized in low temperature physics and quantum chemistry, and authored Superfluids (1950) and numerous articles. The Fritz London Papers include correspondence, notes, manuscripts, reprints, and other materials, with bulk dates 1926-1954. The more than 300 correspondents include Walter Heitler, F.A. Lindemann, Max von Laue, Wolfgang Pauli, Michael Polyani, Erwin Schrödinger, Enrico Fermi, Edward Teller, and other noted scientists. Other materials include galleys and drafts of Superfluids, lab notebooks, course materials, notes, bound reprints. Materials acquired after London's death include interviews with Edith London; memorials; copies of correspondence held in other repositories; selected publications and interview transcripts; and indexes to London's scientific correspondence. English and German.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Provenance
The Fritz London Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1948-2005.
Biographical Note
Fritz Wolfgang London was born in Breslau, Germany (Wrocjaw, Poland) in 1900, brother of Heinz London and son of a professor of mathematics in Bonn. He studied classics at the universities of Frankfurt and Munich and did research in philosophy leading to a doctorate at Bonn. Later he was attracted to theoretical physics and worked with Arnold Sommerfeld at Munich and Erwin Schrodinger at Zurich University in 1927, and published on the quantum theory of the chemical bond with Walter Heitler. In 1930 he calculated the non-polar component of forces between molecules, now called van der Waals or London forces. He and his brother fled from Germany in 1933 to Oxford where they joined Sir Francis Simon's group at the Clarendon Laboratory. Together they published major papers on conductivity giving the London equations (1935). Fritz moved to Duke University in the USA (1939-54) and continued to work on superconductivity and superfluidity.
[Biography from Chambers Biographical Dictionary, 1997]
Collection Overview
The Fritz London Papers include correspondence, notes, manuscripts, reprints, and other materials, with bulk dates 1926-1954. The more than 300 correspondents include Walter Heitler, F.A. Lindemann, Max von Laue, Wolfgang Pauli, Michael Polyani, Erwin Schrödinger, Enrico Fermi, Edward Teller, and other noted scientists. Major subjects include chemistry and theoretical physics, the Nazi regime and its effects on German scientists and academics, and London's emigration from Germany. Other materials include galleys and drafts of Superfluids, 30 lab notebooks, course materials, notes, bound reprints, and a manuscript on the significance of quantum theory for chemistry. Materials acquired after London's death include interviews with Mrs. London; memorials; copies of correspondence held in other repositories; indexes to London's scientific correspondence prepared by Kostas Gavroglou; a bound volume of notes written out by London from lectures given by Prof. Arnold Sommerfeld (1868-1951) at the University of Munich.
Related Material
The German and Jewish Intellectual Émigré Collection.
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, State University of New York.
Bibliography
Gavroglou, Kostas. Fritz London: a scientific biography. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995.
Electric conductivity; Fluids; Helium; London, Fritz, 1900-1954; London, Fritz, 1900-1954; Duke University. Department of Physics; Duke University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1926-1954 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes professional letters and correspondence, with a significant portion in German. Earlier accessions of correspondence (Boxes 1-2) are organized chronologically, while later accessions of correspondence are organized alphabetically by correspondent. There is significant overlap between the two arrangement types, and both should be consulted. An index to the correspondence is available; please contact University Archives for more information. The more than 300 correspondents include Walter Heitler, F.A. Lindemann, Max von Laue, Wolfgang Pauli, Michael Polyani, Erwin Schrödinger, Enrico Fermi, Edward Teller, and other noted scientists.
  - Dec. 1926-1938, [15 folders] (Box 1)
  - 1939-1954 and undated, [10 folders] (Box 2)
  - Translations of selected correspondence with Born, Casimir, and Von Laue (Box 2)
  - Correspondence arranged by correspondent, [A96-76, A99-25, A99-49] (Box 5-6, 11)
    Additional materials written by named correspondents also appear in Box 1 and 2.
- Manuscripts and writings, 1922-1958, 1988-1994
  Includes articles, lectures, reprints, and manuscript drafts written, and sometimes annotated, by London. Also included are writings of London's colleagues, as well as articles and interview about London's life and work, written after his death in 1954.
  - Superfluids, Vols. 1-2, circa 1950-1953, [7 folders] (Box 3)
  - Untitled: Quantum theory and chemical bonds, circa 1930-1931, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Lectures
    - The Structure of the Atom in Chemical Bonding, 1930 (Box 3)
    - Theory of Relativity, circa 1931 (Box 3)
    - Theory of Metals, 1935, [A99-25] (Box 6)
    - On Supraconductivity, 1935 (Box 6)
    - Theory of Reduction, 1936 (Box 6)
    - Theory of Molecular Forces, 1936 (Box 6)
    - Lecture in Whitehead's Seminar, 1936 (Box 6)
    - 1937 (in French) (Box 6)
    - 1938 (Box 6)
    - Math-Chem Seminar, 1940 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - Drafts (Box 6)
  - Articles in German, [6 folders] (Box 7)
  - Galley proof of Superfluids (Box 7)
  - Articles, drafts, and notes, [A99-49, A2005-19] (Box 11)
  - Reprints of Published Articles, 1922-1953, [2 bound volumes] (Volume Tr. R. v.1-2)
  - Writings by others
    - 1943-1958 and undated (Box 3)
    - Transcript of Edith London interview conducted by Steven Heims, 1988, [A97-101] (Box 4)
    - From Philosophy to Physics: The Work of Fritz London, lecture by Kostos Gavroglu, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Memoir of Fritz London by Edith London, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Article reprints (UA2014-0075) (Box 14)
- Course materials, 1928-1952 and undated
  Includes lecture notes and formulas for courses taught by London. Some overlap may exist with the Writings and manuscripts series and the Notes series.
  - Chemical physics, 1940s and undated (Box 4)
  - Electrodynamics, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  - Thermodynamics, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
  - Mechanics, 1930-1931 (Box 4)
  - Quantum mechanics, 1928-1929 (Box 4)
  - Superfluids, 1952, [A2005-19] (Box 11)
- Notes, 1927-1948 and undated
  Includes lab notebooks, note cards, and other notes relating to London's research, writing, and teaching.
  - 1935-1948, [A97-101] (Box 4)
  - Electrodynamik (Box 4)
  - Note cards (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, Oct. 1927-July 1929 (Box 8)
  - Notebooks, Oct. 1929-June 1933 (Box 9)
  - Notebooks, Jan. 1934-Dec. 1942 (Box 10)
- Audio and visual materials, 1987 and undated
  Includes slides of manuscript pages and technical drawings, oversized drawings, and two sound recordings of oral history interviews related to London's life and work.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Oral history interviews require the creation of listening copies before use. Please contact Archives staff prior to visiting the Duke University Archives to access these materials.
  - Slides of manuscript pages and technical drawings (Box 7)
  - Oversized drawings (Map-case 8)
    - Electronic density of two hydrogen atoms with parallel spins (Box 7)
    - Electronic density of two hydrogen atoms with antiparallel spin (Box 7)
  - Oral history interviews with Edith London, Feb. 1987-June 1987, [A90-10]; [10 cassette tapes] (Box 12)
  - Interview with Marcus Hobbs, June 12, 1987, [1 cassette tape] (Box 12)
- Accession UA2010-0003, 1938-2008, 1 box
  This accession includes photocopies of correspondence between Laszlo Tisza and Fritz London, dating from 1938-1952, as well as interview transcripts of Tisza by Kostas Gavroglu (1987-1988), additional correspondence, and copies of selected publications. These materials were received from the MIT Institute Archives and Special Collections, which houses the originals in the Laszlo Tisza Papers (MC 676).
  - Correspondence from Tisza to London, 1938-1952 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence from London to Tisza, 1938-1952 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence between Tisza and R.R. Davis of Physics Today, 1950-1951 (Box 13)
  - Copies of articles from Nature, 1938, and The Electromagnetic Equations of the Supraconductor, by F. and H. London, from The Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, v. A149, 1935, p. 71-88 (from Supraconductivity, Selected Reprints, 1964) (Box 13)
  - Physics Today, v. 11, n. 3, March 1958, p. 11-25 (Box 13)
  - Cooperative Phenomena, symposium in honor of the 80th birthday of Professor Herbert Froehlich, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Les Genies de la Science, Pour la Science, Edition Francaise de Scientific American, May-August 2004 (Box 13)
  - Qui a decouvert la superfluidite? Sebastien Balibar, circa 2001 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1949-2001 (bulk 1949-1969) (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1991 (bulk 1942-1964) (Box 13)
  - Correspondence between Tisza and Edith London, 1953-1974 (Box 13)
  - Transcript of oral history interview with Tisza by Kostas Gavroglu, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Transcripts of interviews with Tisza by Kostas Gavroglu, with edits, 1987-1988 (Box 13)
  - Conference on the History of Thermodynamics (Facts, Trends, Debates), 23-28 July 1990, Veszprem, Hungary, Abstracts of the Conference (Box 13)
  - The Atom and the Apple, Sebastien Balibar, 2008 (copy of the title page and table of contents only) (Box 13)